星际之门  前情回顾
Previously on Stargate Atlantis
我知道你们有个提议
Sir, I understand you had proposals.
我们有个基因治疗方案
We've come up with a gene therapy
能使幽灵族的DNA发生改变
that alters wraith dna.
我认为我们可以实现
we think we can make it
这样你们就不用再以人类为食了
so that you will never need to feed on humans again.
接着
Here.
尝尝这个
Try this.
他是杰纳斯
his name was janus.
因果关系不能轻视
causality is not to be treated so lightly.
没有人轻视它
no one's treating it lightly.
你就是
you are.
你坚持要进行你那实验
you are insistent on continuing the experiment.
我们曾下令要求你停止那项活动
we order you to cease these activities.
这么小题大做有必要么
i don't know what all the fuss is about.
要是每次有人来
if we do this every time
都这么折腾
someone comes for a visit,
我们什么活儿都干不成
we'd never get any work done.
我们只是到门口见见他
we're just meeting him at the gate.
可不是去门口见他那么简单
we're not just meeting him at the gate.
帮他对那数据库进行研究
i've been pulled from my regular duties
已经够折腾我的了
to help him with his database "research".
我还有事儿要忙  你又不是不知道
i've got stuff on the go, you know--
重要的  对于人类的进化
important, vital projects
这可是至关重要的事儿
for the betterment of the human race.
事实上每个人都有
apparently there are other people
跟你一样重要的事情要忙
doing equally important work, rodney,
你难以相信那有多难
as hard as that is to believe.
令人振奋的一天
an exciting day.
的确
absolutely.
传送准备就绪
he's ready to beam.
很好
very well.
杰克森博士  欢迎回到亚特兰蒂斯
dr. jackson, welcome to atlantis.
谢谢  伍尔希先生  能回来真好
thank you, mr. woolsey. it's great to be back.
谢帕德中校  罗德尼
colonel sheppard, rodney...
没问题  当然没有  你有什么打算么
oh, sure, sure. what have you got planned?
对毫无意义的古人历史事件的
an exciting exploration
一次进动人心的探险?
of insignificant ancient historical events?
不  不是那么简单
no, not quite.
有个叫杰纳斯的古人  你们俩应该都很熟悉
i'm sure you're both familiar with the ancient named janus?
那个发明家?
the inventor?
对  他是带头的科学家
yes, he was the lead scientist
骨子里还有些叛逆
and apparently a bit of a renegade.
我最近一直在研究他的日志
yeah, and i've been over all his logs.
瞧瞧  这就是我们的工作成果
look, this is work we've done already.
我敢肯定我已经掌握了一些信息
i'm pretty sure i have information
能带我们找到他的秘密实验室
that could lead us to his secret lab.
秘密实验室?
secret lab?
是的  一个由他创立  后来被用于
yes, a place where he conducted and subsequently hid
藏匿他大部分非法研究的场所
a significant portion of his unauthorized research.
如果没猜错的话  就在这里
and if i'm correct, it's right here...
在亚特兰蒂斯
on atlantis.
我对杰纳斯的数据库
i've been over janus' database entries
进行了地毯式检索
with a fine-tooth comb.
我从没见到有涉及秘密实验室的地方
i never saw any mention of a secret lab.
杰纳斯做了很多工作
janus was doing a lot of work
但都没获得古人委员会的批准
that wasn't exactly approved by the ancient council,
不难想象
so it's not hard to imagine
他也不会把此全部记录在
he wouldn't include a full accounting
这种对外公开的数据库里
in this very public database.
你在官方的报告中
do you include all of your research
提交了所有的研究细节?
in your official reports?
有话直说
just get to the point.
在他的记录里从未涉及过这个
he never talked about it in his entries,
但是杰纳斯的同代人中
but several of janus' peers
有人怀疑他有
suspected he had
"一整个碉堡的自由想法和实验"
a "bastion of unfettered thought and experimentation,"
同时他的一个情人也表示
or as one of his lovers put it--
他有情人?
he had lovers?
"城市墙壁中孤独的小岛"
"an isle of solitude within the city walls."
这可能是说他不善交际
could just mean he was hard to talk to.
过去还有人一直这么说我呢
people say things like that about me all the time.
所有的作者对于
none of these writers had any idea
秘密实验室在哪里都毫无头绪
where the lab could be,
但他的一个年轻的助手
but one of his young assistants
回忆说有一天看他走进一条走廊
recalls a day where janus turned a corner down a hallway.
"今天我看到杰纳斯走进那条走廊"
"today i saw janus in the hallway..."
这真是重要的转折啊(讽刺)
there's a real page-turner.
出于好奇他就跟了上去
he chased after him with a question,
但当他转到走廊上  发现杰纳斯失踪了
but when he rounded the corner, janus was gone.
那条走廊是个死胡同
the hallway was a dead end.
他就那么消失了  我觉得他是进了秘密实验室
he had seemingly disappeared, i think, into his secret lab.
那  他的助手有没有提到
well, did this assistant happen to mention...
哪条走廊是吗  他说了
...which hallway? yes. he does.
代达罗斯号装载完了供给品之后
as soon as the daedalus unloads its supplies,
我们尽快出发
we'll be heading off
去跟托德他们会面
to meet up with todd and one of his hives.
你觉得他真的会露面么
you really think he's going to show up, huh?
还让你的人在他们身上
and let you guys try out dr. keller's gene therapy
试验凯勒博士的基因治疗
on a few of his guys?
放心  我们对这次谈判有把握
well, we held up our end of the deal.
我们可以让他凭借泰勒
we let him use teyla
去掌控幽灵母舰的联盟
to take control of an alliance of wraith hives.
这就是我想说的  他倒是如愿以偿了
that's what i'm saying, he's got what he wants.
我得跟你一块去
i should go with you,
因为我跟托德还有过牵扯
because i have a relationship with todd--
这正是我不让你去的原因
that is precisely why i don't want you there.
这次的任务说白了就是一场谈判
this mission is basically going to be a negotiation,
对于托德
and todd has, well...
对手是我的话  他的精神包袱会更轻些
less baggage with me than he does with you.
我不是说不让你领队
i'm not saying you shouldn't take the lead--
你是这里的副指挥官  上校
you're second in command here, colonel.
我知道我的前任对于
i know my predecessors played fast and loose
组织的一些规矩睁只眼闭只眼
with many of the rules set forth by the i.o.a.,
但是协议上很明确的表示
but protocol plainly states
在少数情况下
that in the rare instance
如果我必须要离开亚特兰蒂斯
where i am required to leave atlantis,
你得留下
you stay put.
在我回来之前这里你管
you're in command here until i get back.
明白吗
understood?
好吧
okay.
我不在的时候小心别出乱子
try not to blow her up while i'm gone.
我可不敢保证
no promises.
好了  这应该是最后一个了
yeah, i think this should be the last of it.
我正要走呢
i was just leaving.
我知道
yeah, i know.
来  我帮你拿
here, let me get that.
谢谢
thanks.
你要去代达罗斯号了?
so you're going on this daedalus thing?
谢谢
thank you.
这也是没办法的事儿
i kind of have to.
我是这里唯一懂得这种疗法的人
i'm the one that'll be administering the treatment...
这个我们之前也有谈到过
if, you know, we ever get to that point.
对
right.
我觉得我有必要跟你一块去
i think i should come with you on this.
真的  为什么
really? why?
我信不过那些家伙
i don't really trust these guys.
你信不过托德和幽灵族
you don't trust todd and his wraith
还是说代达罗斯号上的人员
or the entire crew of the daedalus
你担心我出事儿  想来保护我?
to protect me if something goes wrong?
不好说
i don't know.
可能两者都有吧
both, i guess.
什么
what?
没什么
nothing.
想说就说吧
what?
没什么  真没什么
nothing, nothing.
有你陪着感觉挺好的
it'd be great to have the company.
再见  罗德尼  祝我们好运
bye, rodney. wish us luck.
好运
good luck.
你说"我们"是什么意思
what do you mean, "us"?
罗德尼  你...
rodney... you, uh...?
那儿是不是有条水管?
is that a water line up there?
是的  在我们到这里的第一年
yeah, this section of the city flooded
这里就被淹了
the first year we were here.
有利用价值的东西
anything salvageable
都被转移到了主塔上
got moved to the main tower.
这里地处偏僻  看起来有希望
it's remote. that's promising.
在他到秘密实验室的时候
he wouldn't want anyone around
肯定不希望有人在附近的
when he came in and out of his lab.
真像个蝙蝠洞
like the bat cave.
是阿  就像个蝙蝠洞
yes... just like the bat cave.
到目前为止还没发现什么独特的东西
i'm not picking up anything unusual...
这儿曾经有东西
something used to be attached here.
嗯  这里也有
hmm. and here...
这儿还有
and another one.
知道是什么吗
any idea what they are?
好像是粗制的烛台插槽
looks like a run-of-the-mill sconce interface.
嗯  问题是烛台在哪里
right. well, where are the sconces?
我怎么知道
i don't know.
可能负责装修的人突然改变了主意
maybe the decorator changed his mind.
你刚才说在洪水之后
you said after the flood,
所有有价值的东西
anything worth salvaging
都被转移到了主塔上
was moved to the main tower.
那但愿你能告诉我你有记录
now, please tell me you kept detailed records
关于那些东西都在哪儿发现的
of what was found and where.
我们有没有详细记录?  你当我是谁啊
did we keep detailed records? who are you talking to here?
这儿  这就是那个走廊
there. that's the hallway.
能放大点么
can you zoom in there?
这儿  这儿就是固定灯的地方
there. there are your light fixtures.
肯定是在被淹的时候
must have been knocked loose
被水泡松了
during the flood.
有可能
possibly.
你们抢救出了这些  对吧?
but you salvaged them, right?
这是在洪水期间掉落的灯具
they're lights that fell during a flood--
就顺顺我  好不好
just humor me, okay?
我觉得我们快有戏了
i think we're onto something.
好吧
all right.
在这儿呢
here they are.
找到了
i've got 'em.
奇怪
that's odd.
将三盏灯插亮时
each of these three lights made a different tone
它们发出三种不同的音调
when i plugged them in.
这儿有过类似的事吗
does that usually happen around here?
不常有  没有
not usually, no.
这些灯左碰右撞
they've been banged around a lot,
又被水淹了几天
underwater a few days.
估计是坏了
maybe they're just broken.
不  这是个谜题
no, it's a puzzle.
我想应该通过特定的顺序
i think we need to activate these
可将其激活
in a specific order.
三位数密码?
a 3-digit code?
你知道那破解起来有多容易?
you know how easy that would be to break?
也就6种可能
there's only 6 variations.
也许要几次组合
maybe activate them a number of times
才可以激活它们
in a specific order.
这三个音符有没有让你想到什么
i don't suppose you recognize any of these three notes?
这让我想到
like, does it remind me
杰纳斯最喜欢的布莱恩·伊诺音乐(音节超级少的)
of janus' favorite brian eno track?
不可能  绝没那么好运
no. no such luck.
杰纳斯的助理说他嗖的一下
janus' assistant said he disappeared pretty quickly
就从走廊消失了
down the hallway,
因此密码肯定不长
so it can't be a long code.
或许就是简单的3个连续音
maybe it's as simple as 3 tones in a row.
慢慢试吧
go for it.
等等
hold on for a second.
怎么了
what is it?
过来抵着墙
come here and push against this wall.
为什么
why?
拜托  照我说的做
please. just humor me.
我有主意了
i think i'm on to something.
好了  我数到三
okay, on the count of three,
你就用力推墙  行吗
push against the wall as hard as you can, okay?
行
okay.
好了  一  二  三
okay. one... two... three...
娘的
son of a bitch.
可控制磁性谐波共振
controlled magnetic harmonic resonance.
啥
what?
显然爱迪生在泰斯拉快要成功之前
apparently tesla was close to something like this
毁了他的实验室
before edison trashed his lab.
你在说什么呢
what are you talking about?
这堵墙是特别设计的
that wall was specially designed
当其不断收到
to de-stablize
特定的谐波共振时
when bombarded
就会变得不稳定
with a very specific harmonic resonance.
那些音就是这个作用
that's what the tones were.
周围强烈的磁性粒子
and the strong magnetic property of the particles
可以防止门瓦解
is what keeps the door from just crumbling into dust.
用这种方法掩藏门真是绝了
it's a great way to hide a door,
当你想打开门时
because if you're looking for a door to open,
恐怕想找到都难
it's never going to be found.
类似全息照相  只是更加逼真
it's like a hologram, only better,
因为在音频响起之前  那儿就是一堵墙
because it's solid mass until the tones are playing.
你刚刚完全可以让我
so you could have just told me
走过这扇门
to walk through the door.
确实可以
i could have, yes.
是啊  是啊
yes, yes.
我们这到底是在哪儿
where the hell are we?
杰纳斯的秘密实验室
janus' secret lab.
通知其他人
alert the others.
仪器激活了
the device has been activated.
伍尔希先生
hey, mr. woolsey.
凯勒医生
dr. keller.
你那剽悍的保镖呢
where is your burly protector?
他不在你身边反倒挺不习惯的
it's odd to see you without him nowadays.
他在实验室里
he's in the lab.
你在忙什么呢
what are you working on?
演讲
a speech.
为了什么
what for?
这是个相当重要的场合
well, this is a fairly momentous occasion.
幽灵愿意走近一步
the wraith will take a step forward,
不仅仅为了他们自身利益
not only for their own benefit,
也是为了整个星系
but for that of the entire galaxy.
这是历史性的时刻
it's a historic day.
我觉得他们需要些认可
i just think it deserves some recognition.
那现在进展如何
what have you got so far?
"今天是个历史性的时刻"
"today is an historic day."
开头不错
it's a good place to start.
只是个半成品而已
well, it's a work in progress.
太酷了
whoa. that's pretty cool.
谐波共振
harmonic resonance.
是啊  听人说了
yeah, i was told.
如果音频没了
but what happens if the sound goes off
人还在墙中间怎么办
and you're in the middle of the wall?
那就等着门把你的身体分两半吧
the wall would break apart your body.
那我们应该
maybe we should--
我在门外建立了一个次声波音频发射器
i've set up a sub-sonic tone generator outside.
门就一直开着了
the wall is now permanently open.
别担心
don't worry.
很好  目前进展如何
good. so, what have we got?
好消息是
the good news is
这里的确是杰纳斯的秘密实验室
it's definitely janus' secret lab.
坏消息是  进入这儿是最简单的
the bad news is getting in was the easy part.
这儿所有的数据
there are levels of encryption
都加了密
on all data here
即使是最变态的国家安全局探员
that even the most paranoid nsa agent
也没法搞定
wouldn't use.
我是说  很深奥
i mean, it is deep.
有些就是数字密码
some of them are straight-up math ciphers,
而有些是古人文明的谜题
while others are ancient knowledge puzzles.
除非我们开始解密
and until we start deciphering,
否则没法知道这些是什么意思
there's no way to tell what any of this stuff does.
看来你们合作的不错
sounds like you guys make a good team, though.
是啊
yeah.
那么我回去继续当我的老大了
well, i guess i'll go back to being the boss.
感觉怎么样
how's that going?
无聊透顶
pretty boring, actually.
你若来帮我们
you're more than welcome
搞定这第一个流密码就更好了
to help us crack this first stream cipher.
他可进过门萨(一个高智商协会)
you know, he could have been in mensa.
等你们两个天才有突破时
why don't you contact me
记得通知我
when you two geniuses have a breakthrough.
会的
will do.
长官  有人呼我们
sir, we're being hailed.
打开通道
open a channel.
我是代达罗斯号上的卡德威尔上校
this is colonel caldwell of the earth ship daedalus.
正准备接待您的代表团
we're ready to receive your delegation.
代表团已经上路了
the delegation is on their way.
马克斯你开好舰桥
marks, you have the bridge.
我要去会客了
i'm going to meet our guests.
谢谢你们的光临
thank you for coming.
谢谢你们的邀请
thank you for having us.
今天是历史性的时刻
today is an historic day.
格罗斯泰斯特曾经说过
robert grosseteste once said--
我希望能尽快开始
i would like to get started as soon as possible.
好吧  当然啦
yes, of course.
但我仍想认可一下
but i wanted to recognize--
我很怀疑
i have my doubts
你们的计划是否有效
that your plan will be effective.
还是跳过
so shall we drop
多余的客套话
these unfounded pleasantries
直接切入主题吧
and get to work?
很好
very well.
凯勒医生
dr. keller,
请带路
lead the way.
请跟我来
please, come with me.
罗伯特什么?
robert who?
甭管了
never mind.
天都快亮了
you know, it's almost dawn.
如果这还能叫晚上的话
if you want to call it a night...
什么  不不不  我很好  没问题
what? no, no, no, i'm fine, fine.
你想休息的话
but if you need to rest,
我完全理解
i'll completely understand.
说真的  你是不是把每件事都看作竞争呢
seriously, is everything a competition with you?
我不知道你在说什么
i'm not sure what you're talking about.
帮你找到一个秘密实验室
i just found you a secret lab
里面满是很棒的古人物品
full of really cool ancient stuff.
你总该给我记一功吧
i kind of think that should score me some points.
好吧  我承认
okay, i will admit
我对你确实有一点无礼
that i may have been a little brusque with you.
一点?
just a little.
事实上
the truth is,
我并不认为你会有什么发现
i really didn't think you would find anything.
这我理解
well, that much i actually understand.
真的?
you do?
是的
yeah.
我的理论绝大多数时候
i've spent the majority of my professional life
都是被嘲笑的对象
being ridiculed for my theories,
但最终总是被证明是对的
most of which turned out to be correct,by the way.
我已经习惯了  罗德尼
i'm kind of used to it, rodney.
你不介意吗
doesn't that bother you?
没有辩解  没有认可  没有功勋
i mean, no vindication, no recognition, no credit...
你又何尝不是
i could say the same thing about you.
你的迄今为止的那些发现
the discoveries you've made,
恐怕能得5个诺贝尔奖
you probably could've won the nobel prize
也不止吧
five times over by now.
是呀
too true.
看来我们都不是为了名声的人
so, i guess none of us signed up to get famous, huh?
是啊  也就混口饭吃
no, we did it for the money.
说得好
good one.
等等
wait a minute--
你不会比我拿的多吧  会吗
you don't get paid more than i do, do you?
会吗
do you?
超空间窗口刚打开
hyperspace window just opened.
代达罗斯号还没到时间回来啊
daedalus isn't due back yet.
去找谢帕德
get sheppard.
谢帕德中校
colonel sheppard, sir?
在  小睡了一下
yeah, uh, just resting my eyes.
谁在说话
who said that?
我破解了您房间的广播系统
i patched into the pa in your room, sir.
您最好赶紧过来
you're going to want to get up here.
出了什么事
what's going on?
我们正在跟踪一架小型飞船  在大气层中
we're tracking a small ship, in atmosphere.
它朝我们过来了
It's coming right for us.
把飞船放出去
Get the jumpers in the air.
它来得很快
It's closing fast, sir.
10秒之内就会到了
It'll be here in less than 10 seconds.
打开防护罩
Shields up.
飞船同时也准备好
I still want the jumpers ready.
来了
Here it comes...
不可能
That's impossible.
它刚做了什么
What did it just do?
它穿过了防护罩
It passed through the shield.
我知道  关键是它是怎么做到的
Yeah, but how did it do that?
我不太确定
I'm not sure, sir.
但好像古人飞船可以
Ancient ships can do it.
叫泰勒带一支分队
All right, tell Teyla and a team of marines
到那个码头来和我会合
to meet me at that pier.
他们应该就在你们前面
They should be right in front of you.
别动
Don't move!
这底下到底有什么
What's at the bottom of this tower?
罗德尼
Rodney.
罗德尼  这里是谢帕德  请回话
Rodney, this is Sheppard. come in.
罗德尼
Rodney!
什么事
What's up?
马上离开那儿
Get out of there right now.
为什么
Why?
控制室  那艘飞船现在是什么情况
Control room, what's the status of that ship?
对不起  中校
I'm sorry, Colonel.
他们走了
They're gone.
它还活着吗
Is it alive?
我问你呢
You tell me.
读数不连贯
I'm not getting any coherent readings.
也许我们要用医学扫描仪
Perhaps we should put it under a medical scanner.
好  那就这样做
Okay, do it.
拿个轮床来
Go get a gurney.
它真的劫持了罗德尼和杰克森博士?
So is it true they took Rodney and Dr. Jackson?
对
Yeah.
见鬼  怎么回事
What the hell happened?
我们被攻击了
We were attacked.
这我知道  谢谢
That much I got, thanks.
谁做的
By who?
我还想你来告诉我呢
I was kind of hoping you could tell me.
好了  这绝不是巧合
Okay, there is no way this is a coincidence.
我们发现了杰纳斯的秘密实验室
We discover Janus' super-secret lab,
而24小时之内
and less than 24 hours later,
一群外星人带着枪出现
a bunch of aliens show up, all guns blazing?
不觉得奇怪吗
Don't think that's a little odd?
你这么一说...
Now that you mention it...
他们十分确定自己要找什么
They knew exactly what they were looking for.
不浪费一点时间  直奔实验室
Didn't waste any time, went straight for the lab.
他们出来的时候  一个人拿着个仪器
When they came out, one of them was carrying a device.
不幸的是
Unfortunately,
我们根本没时间
we haven't had nearly enough time
检查完所有的东西
to go through everything we found in here,
所以也不可能知道
so there's no way of knowing
他们到底拿了什么
exactly what they took.
罗德尼和杰克森博士一进来
All this stuff came on
这些东西就自行运作起来了
when Rodney and Dr. Jackson came in here.
差不多
Pretty much.
它几乎就是因为
It activated
罗德尼的a.t.a.基因而激活  怎么了
probably in response to Rodney's a.t.a. gene. why?
如果这里有什么一直在发送信息呢
What if something in here has been broadcasting?
来自亚空间的信号  只有这种可能
A subspace signal-- it's the only possible answer.
你在说什么
What are you talking about?
我们之前遇到过
We've come across them before.
两个古人仪器中
They're a real-time, practically instantaneous link
存在着一种实时的联系
between two ancient devices.
就算相距半个银河  仍可以工作
They can be separated by, like, half a galaxy.
外边有一群外星人
There's a bunch of aliens out there.
他们偶然间发现一个古人实验室
They stumble upon an ancient lab,
估计就是杰纳斯自己造的
probably built by Janus himself.
处于休眠状态  不能运作
It's dormant. It's not working.
某一天  它突然激活了
Then one day, out of the blue, it activates.
他们围在一起  抓耳挠腮
So they're standing around, scratching they're heads.
不知道是怎么回事
They have no idea what's going on.
然后  他们发现了亚空间连接
Then they discover the subspace link.
他们打算跟踪它
They decide to follow it,
一路追踪找到了我们
they trace it back to us.
然后攻击了我们  还抓了两个当人质?
And then attack us and take two of our people hostage?
他们的目标不是罗德尼和杰克森博士
Rodney and Dr. Jackson were not the targets.
他们只是在错误的时间呆在了错误的地方
They were at the wrong place at the wrong time.
不管是什么仪器  那才是他们要的
Whatever that device was, that's what they were after.
好吧  推理得不错
All right, good theory.
那我们该怎么办
So what do we do?
我们...我们得先离开这儿
Well, we... we've got to get out of here.
我们很可能在一艘超空间旅行的飞船上
We're probably on a ship traveling through hyperspace.
我们会去哪儿
Where are we going to go?
我会想出点办法的
I'll think of something.
真的?
Really?
当然  一直都是
Yep. Always do.
哦对了  那我试过了
Oh yeah, I tried that.
你一碰到他们  他们就会电你
They zap you when you touch them.
你可以在我碰之前就告诉我
You could told me that before I touched it.
我是可以
I could have, yes.
他们什么都没给我们
Look, they stripped us
只有身后的一些衣服
of everything but the clothing on our backs
和周围的一圈激光墙
and surrounded us with laser walls...
我可想不出我们还能干点什么
I'm not sure how much play we have here.
至少还有一点是有利我们的
We've got one thing going for us, at least.
什么
What's that?
我们还没死
We're not dead yet.
说得好
Good point.
没用
It's no good.
还是没有读到有用的信息
I'm still not getting any useful readings.
这套装备发出了某种防护
The suit is emitting some sort of e.m. field
干扰了扫描仪
That's disrupting the scanner.
我完全不知道如何停掉它
I have no idea how to shut it off.
能不能穿透这层防护
There's no way to penetrate the shield
看清里面的情况?
and see what's under there?
我想不能
I'm afraid not.
盔甲下面会不会是个人
Do you think there's a human underneath all that armor?
不太可能  应该是个机器人
Impossible to say. Could be a robot.
有件事是肯定的
One thing's for sure--
这和我们见过的都不同
It's not like anything we've ever seen before.
韦尔博士的确说过
Dr. Weir did say that there were other
我们还会遇到其他
technologically advanced societies
科技高度发达的群体
that we have yet to encounter.
这是我们的"第一次亲密接触"
We've just made first contact.
你们要我做什么
What do you want me to do?
切开
Cut it open.
没用  锋口都钝了
It's no good. I just dulled the blade.
脖子
The neck.
什么
What?
看上去应该是最柔软的部分
Looks like the softest part.
试试从脖子入手
Try the neck.
它已经死了  拉迪克
It's already dead, Radek.
只是我们这么认为
We think.
你只管做
Just do it.
行得通
It's working!
出去  所有人出去
Get out. Everyone, get out!
大家都还好吗
Everyone okay?
是的
Yes.
不管装备下有什么
Somebody really wants to keep secret
他们不想让别人知道
whatever's inside that suit.
我们对在押的幽灵人
We've run close to a hundred simulations
进行了上百个
based on full medical scans
完整医学扫描模拟
of the wraith we've had in captivity.
都很成功
They've all been successful.
我们都知道
We both know very well
计算机模拟和实体试验
that computer simulations and live trials
有很大的不同
are very different.
我不认为我们是自夸的
I don't think we're doing this cavalierly.
我有数据为证
I stand by the data.
它能行
It will work.
也许能行
Perhaps it will.
问题是  你想它成功吗
The question is, do you want it to?
我的确看到了它的好处
I do see the benefits.
即使只是用在我的一些部队上
Even if we only used the therapy on some of my troops...
他们的生命  因为战争的关系
Say, those whose lives, thanks to this war,
都很短暂
are expected to be short.
为什么把那么好的资源浪费在他们身上
Why waste perfectly good resources on them, yes?
但要我为了人类的利益
But it will be very difficult for me
牺牲我周围的一些人
to ask those around me to give themselves over
我还办不到
for the good of the human race.
也是为了你们的利益
But it's for your benefit too.
如果你们不必再以人类为食
If you don't have to rely on human feeding,
战争就可以结束了
the war would be over.
也许...
Perhaps...
那然后我们做什么呢
But then what would we do?
我们又是谁呢
Who would we be?
我们能和负责人谈谈吗
Can we talk to somebody in charge?
我认为这里有些误会
I think there's been a bit of a misunderstanding.
没必要这样对待我们
There's no need to treat us this way...
运行仪器
Get the device operational.
我都不知道那是什么
I don't even know what it is!
太妙了
Oh, great.
关得密不透风
It's sealed shut,
而且还把控制器拿走了
and they've removed the door controls from this side.
我们到底在什么鬼地方
Where the hell are we?
从建筑风格上来看
I'd say judging by the lantian architecture,
我猜  是杰纳斯的秘密基地
I'd guess, you know, secret Janus facility.
这可对我们不利
Which is, you know, probably bad for us,
因为这意味着这里很难被找到
because it probably means it's hard to find.
也就是说近期内不会有人来营救了
So I guess that means no rescue any time soon.
你觉得看着眼熟吗
Does that look familiar to you?
是啊  亚特兰蒂斯实验室里的仪器
Yeah, it's the device from the Atlantis lab.
至少知道他们为什么要带我们过来了
At least we know why they brought us with them.
他们要我们帮助启动这个设备
they need us to get the device operational.
我知道他们的意图
i caught that.
我想我们不会从外面的健谈先生们那里
right, and i don't think we'll get any more info
得到什么信息了
from talky mcsays-a-lot out there,
那就启动控制台
so fire up these consoles,
看看我们要跟什么打交道
see what we're dealing with.
不是那个
not like that.
等下  可能是这个
um... let's see. yeah, like that.
还得按这个
and then i need to be right there, yep.
谢谢
thanks. there.
现在有五艘飞船在我们上空
we've got five jumpers in the air
摆成了防御阵形
flying a defensive formation around the city
飞船已经为你准备好了
and have the chair fired up and ready for you
可以立刻使用
at a moment's notice.
每五层都要有一个分队
i want marine details every five levels,
全副武装 时刻听我指令
locked and loaded, ready for my go-ahead,
以防万一
just in case.
没问题
absolutely.
中校  我想我找到了点东西
colonel, i think i may have something.
我按照你提出的假设
i've been working under the assumption
他们带走的设备
that, as you suggested,
在发出
the device they took
某种亚空间信息
must have been broadcasting
据此进行研究
some sort of subspace communication.
你能够追踪到吗
you can trace it?
如果是从亚特兰蒂斯发的话就能
if it was broadcasting from atlantis, yes.
不过明显已经不在了
but obviously it's not doing that anymore.
所以呢...
so...
所以...
我用拉兹洛·巴拜的理论
well, i'm using the work of laszlo babai
做基础
as a stepping stone.
你知道那些组合数学  还有...
you know, combinatorics and, um...
别见怪
no offense,
但是那些数学太复杂了
but the math i'm using is so complicated
不知道我能不能
that i don't know if i can dumb it down enough
让你明白
for it to make sense.
不试怎么知道
try.
好吧
all right, well, okay,
我正在查看记录下来的亚空间日志
i've been going over our recorded subspace logs
尝试找到一条
and i'm trying to extrapolate the single thread
能把我们带到那个仪器附近
that will lead us to the area of space
的路线
associated with the device.
明白了
well, i understand that.
很难准确描述出我现在做的事  不过...
it doesn't accurately represent what i'm doing, but--
我知道了
i get it.
这事很难
what you're doing is difficult.
有进展的时候跟我说一声
just tell me when you get a hit.
这个机器
this facility is tapped into
接入了一个非常强大的发电系统
some pretty serious power generation.
以前从没见过这种玩意儿
i've never seen anything like it before.
得要很多能量...
you'd need a lot of power...
什么
what?
我知道这个东西干吗用的了
i think i know what this thing does.
什么
what?
这是终端机器
it's an endgame machine.
什么意思
how so?
如果和我想的一样的话
if it works the way i think it does,
那它能让幽灵族
it would mean the end of the wraith
永远消失
once and for all.
怎么能把幽灵
so how do you destroy the wraith
彻底毁灭
once and for all?
我可没说  毁灭
well, i never said "destroy."
我是说  可能会那样
i mean, it would lead to that, i suppose,
这个设备
but this device
将会把他们送上死亡之路
would stop them dead in their tracks.
怎么送
how?
它能制造一种特定的亚空间静电...
it creates a very specific subspace static...
用紊流来形容可能更好点
turbulence is a better way of looking at it.
然后
which...
听着
okay, look.
尽管他们都是依据
although they're all based
一个很类似的技术造成的
on a fairly similar technological premise,
但是每种都有不同的
each race has a slightly different type
超空间引擎系统
of hyperdrive.
我们用的是改造过的
ours are based on the asgard drives
仙宫驱动
with our own little twist.
古人有自己的系统
the ancients had their own system,
还有幽灵
and the wraith, again,
也有自己独立的超空间引擎技术
have their own separate hyperdrive technology.
好吧
all right.
最简单的
so at its base level,
超空间引擎能够通过进出亚空间
a hyperdrive allows you to travel great distances
加大飞行距离
by entering and exiting subspace.
这个我知道
okay, this much i already know, yes.
所以  要是这个机器
okay, so, if this machine
能正常运转
is capable of actually functioning safely,
就会瓦解
it disrupts
幽灵使用的
the very specific subspace frequencies
特殊的亚空间频率
the wraith use.
然后他们就不能再用超空间引擎了
so they wouldn't be able to engage their hyperdrives.
真是天才  可惜不是
that's the genius-- they would be able to.
他们独有的亚空间轨道
it's just that their particular channel of subspace
不稳定
would be destabilized
飞船会被
and the ship would be ripped
撕的粉碎
into a million pieces.
机器运转起来之后
when this device is turned on,
一旦幽灵船进入超空间
every time a wraith ship enters hyperspace,
就会自爆吗
it self-destructs?
对
yeah.
这注意不错
that's a pretty effective idea.
等其他幽灵知道
because even if word got back to the other wraith
飞船不能使用超空间引擎的时候
that the ships should stop using their hyperdrives,
他们已经被困住了
they'd be stuck where they were.
他们只能用小型引擎
they could only travel using sublight engines.
因为古人飞船的超空间引擎
because ancient ships' hyperdrives operated
的频率和亚空间不同
on a different frequency of subspace,
古人就能把它们挨个收拾了
the ancients could fly around and pick them off one by one.
或者把他们仍在广袤的太空中死去
yeah, or just leave them to die in the vastness of space.
问题在哪儿
so, what's the catch?
问题是
ah, well, the catch is
由于
that janus ran a three-day test
未知因素的影响
about 10,000 years ago
那个研究
and then shut the whole project down
万年前的实验  杰纳斯做了三天就停止了
because of "unforeseen side effects".
什么未知影响
right, which were?
不太清楚
well, it's not clear.
不过那是问题的关键
but that's the key to the whole shebang.
杰纳斯把它带回了亚特兰蒂斯
janus brought that back to atlantis
但仍然与主机相连
but kept it connected to the main system here.
要运作  二者缺一不可
one won't work without the other.
似乎他们确信我们可以操作
they seem pretty convinced we can make it operational.
因为我们有可能
because we probably can.
这儿什么都有
we have everything we need here.
问题是该不该这么做
the question is whether we should.
上次我这么做的时候
the last time i went down this road,
差点毁了一个太阳系
i... i kind of destroyed a solar system.
我也不想
yeah, and i'm not too keen
亲身体验那些什么未知影响
about experiencing those "unforeseen side effects".
那我们要怎么做
so what do we do?
很简单
it's simple.
和他们理论
we, uh... we reason with them?
很明显  你们知道
Now, obviously you're as excited
能够在银河系
about the possibility of ending the wraith's reign
彻底消灭幽灵后很激动
over this galaxy once and for all.
不过现实是
but the reality is
出于某种原因
this device and this facility
制造者
were abandoned by their creator
抛弃了这个设施
for a very good reason.
所以  它不能工作...
see, uh, it doesn't work...
至少不能安全的工作
at least not safely.
就像我朋友说的那样
that's from what my friend can tell.
我们目的相同
look, we share the same goal.
也许还有很多其他共同之处
perhaps we have many things in common.
只要时间充足
look, given the right amount of time,
也许我们能让这个设备
it's possible we could get the device
安全运转
to function safely,
前提是得跟自己人联系
but we'd have to contact our people
找个强大点的科学队来
and bring in a much larger science team.
我不是那块料
see, i'm not that kind of scientist,
我朋友要是
and my friend here--
一小时内让机器运作起来
get the device operational within one hour
否则我就杀了他
or i will kill him.
明白了没
do you understand?
明白了
i understand. yes.
计划不错  丹尼
great plan, danny.
计划不错
great plan.
为什么穿着外套
why the suits?
他们现在不需要作战了
well, they're not in battle anymore.
开始我还以为
originally i thought
这是他们的作战服
it was just their version of swat gear,
可现在他们还穿着
but they still have it on.
也许不只是盔甲那么简单
maybe they're more than just armor.
可能是某种防护服
maybe they're some sort of protective suit.
也许他们不能在我们的大气中生活
maybe they can't function in our livable atmosphere.
也许我们应该把这先放一边
maybe we should just add it to the list of things
这和我们手头的工作没关系
that have nothing to do with the task at hand.
这些盔甲也许是
those suits might be the key
弄清楚这些人身份的关键
to figuring out who these guys really are.
你去了解他们
well, you work on understanding them.
我来保护我们的小命
i'll work on trying not to get us killed.
有进展了吗
well, you got something for me?
是的  那儿
yes. there.
m6h-987
m6h-987.
这是我觉得最可能的
that's my best guess.
确定吗
are you sure?
80%的可能性
well, about 80% sure.
这是唯一的线索  必须这么做
it's our only lead. i'll have to do.
上面没有星门  是吧
doesn't happen to have a gate on it, does it?
是的
no.
当然不会有
of course not.
代达罗斯号仍然联系不上吗
daedalus still out of communications range?
对
yeah, i'm afraid so.
和托德碰头的地点附近也没有星门
their rendezvous point with todd isn't even near a stargate.
我要你去飞船舱
I need you to get to the jumper bay,
尽力扩大亚空间
boost its subspace communications range
通讯范围
as much as you can.
你有什么计划
what are you planning?
我们得尽快赶到那星球去
we've got to get to that planet as soon as possible.
我们乘飞船靠近代达罗斯号
we'll gate as near as we can to the daedalus with a jumper,
让他们帮忙把飞船路线设定好
have them pick us up en route to the planet.
好的  半小时搞定
okay. give me half an hour.
我去让小组准备
i'm going to get the team ready.
主舱室已连接上亚空间
that main chamber houses the subspace antenna.
这会产生亚空间的静电干扰
it harnesses the static into subspace.
一旦开启就会这样
it will once i light it up.
什么  你早准备好了?
what? you're already ready?
它没坏掉  只不过是停下来了
well, it wasn't broken. he just shut it down.
你所需要的仅仅是
all you need is that,
对杰纳斯的编码模式有个基本了解
a basic understanding of janus' coding style,
然后我又要说了
and here's where i come in again,
古人基因
the ancient gene.
我们已经准备好了
we're ready to roll.
罗德尼  你没必要这样做
rodney, you don't have to do this.
什么
what?
要是把这东西开启了
if turning this thing on
意味着太阳能系统就会崩溃
means a solar system is going to explode,
那就不做
then let's not.
他们想要杀了你啊  我们没的选择
they're going to kill you. we don't have a choice.
不  我们有选择
yes, we do.
好吧  我啥也不干
okay, so i do nothing,
他们过来  然后干掉你
they come in here, they kill you.
接着会是谁  是我!
who gets killed next, huh? me.
跟你说实话  我还不想那么早死
to tell you the truth here, i'm quite fond of me,
所以最好趁你还活着的时候做
so might as well do it now while you're still alive
以防...你知道吧
as opposed to, you know, then.
好吧
all right.
好的
好的...
all right...
你还活着?
you still alive?
我看是
i think so.
我可不觉得天堂样该这样子
i'd hate to think heaven looks like this.
谁说我们去的是天堂?
who says we went to heaven?
正在运行
it's operational.
有什么异常?
anything out of the ordinary?
没啊  一切都正常的
no. everything is in the green.
我是说运行良好
i mean, it's working great.
那些"不可预测的副作用"呢?
what about those "unforeseen side effects"?
当然还不可预测啊
they're still unforeseen.
至少现在  运转正常  我们也还活着
for now, it's working, and we're still alive.
好吧  那现在怎么办
okay, so, what now?
也许...我们该庆祝一下
uh, maybe, uh, a nice pat on the back
然后班师回亚特兰蒂斯?
and an all-expense-paid trip back to atlantis?
母舰传给你一条紧急信息
you have an urgent message from your hive.
我觉得你回想私下接听
i assumed you'd want to take it privately.
说吧
go ahead.
很好
very well.
批准!
permission granted.
我还得留在这里
i shall remain here.
没事吧?
is everything okay?
我们的一个设施
one of our facilities is under attack
遭到对手母舰的袭击
by a rival hive.
我们的两艘飞船必须去支援
our two support ships must depart for battle.
我的母舰还会呆在这里
my hive will remain here,
继续配合凯勒医生的工作
continue the work with dr. keller.
非常好
i'm glad to hear that.
哦  不是说被攻击好  那个太不幸了
oh, not the under attack part, that's unfortunate, of course.
我意思是...
i just meant--
算了
never mind.
马克斯  刚才怎么回事
marks, what the hell just happened?
你们怎么做到的
how did you do that?
我们怎么...
how did we--
你当然知道我们和这没关系
surely you don't think we had anything to do with that.
你们欺骗我
you've tricked me.
什么
what?
你们蓄谋已久了
this was your plan all along.
你们早就找到了设备
somehow, you've found the attero device.
什么  我们不知道你...
the what? we have no idea what you--
指挥官
commander,
我们尝试跟你联系
we've been trying to contact you.
另一艘攻击舰已被摧毁
the other cruisers were destroyed.
我知道了
i know.
我们上当了
we've been betrayed.
那我们该怎么办
what should we do?
我已经控制了他们的运输系统
i have control of the humans' transport system.
马上传送我们的部队过去
i'll begin beaming in our troops immediately.
船是我们的了
we're taking the ship
快
come on.
怎么了?
what's going on?
我们遭袭击了
we're under attack.
我们得去给你弄支枪  快点来
we got to get to the armory and get you a gun. come on.
锁住了
locked.
若楠!
ronon!
我们被困在里面了
we're locked in.
这样会拖延他们的行动
that should limit their movements.
继续传送部队
continue beaming in our troops.
十分钟了  还没问题
10 minutes and counting. still no problem.
哦  伙计...
oh, boy...
怎么了
what? what is it?
我想我刚发现了一个日志
i think i just found a log entry
说明了副作用是什么样的
that tells what the side effect is.
不是什么有害辐射吧
it's not harmful radiation, is it?
不不不  咱俩还安全
no. no, no, no. you and i are safe.
我是指银河系其他地方
it's just the rest of the galaxy
可能有问题了  包括亚特兰蒂斯
that's going to have problems, including atlantis.
我得把这个关掉
i've got to shut this thing down.
离开设备
step away from the device.
好 好 等等 等等
okay, wait.
设备现在有个非常严重的故障
there's a very dangerous, serious problem with the device,
我们得跟你们的....
and we need to talk to your boss--
好了  都设定好了
okay, all set.
我让恰克向m54-179星球拨号了
i'll have chuck dial m5r-179.
一旦你到了那里
you should be able to contact the  daedalus
就能通过亚空间
Via subspace
跟代达罗斯号联系上了
once you get there.
干得好
nice work.
谢了  祝好运
thanks. good luck.
多谢  这会派上用场的
thanks, we're going to need it.
好了  拨号吧
all right, dial up.
怎么了
what's that?
黑洞出现了个能量脉冲
we've got a power spike at the event horizon.
什么  能量堆积在星门?
what? power is building within the gate?
不不不  那不可能
no, no, no. that can't happen.
中校  别把飞船降到星门的位置
colonel, do not lower the jumper into the gate room.
怎么了
why not?
出于某种原因
for some reason,
有未知能源
there's an unprecedented power build-up
在星门周围堆积起来
within the gate.
从哪开始堆积?
power build-up from where?
从黑洞里
it's coming from within the event horizon.
哦  不
oh, no.
这对我们非常不利
this is very, very bad for us.
快把它关了
just shut it down.
可能是另一端某个瑕疵门吧
it's probably a faulty gate at the other end.
我  我正在试  可是不管用
i'm-- i'm trying. it won't let me.
好的  我马上下去
all right, i'm coming down.
我们怎么办  再等38分钟
what do we do, wait 38 minutes
然后通过"跳跃者"出去?
and ride the puddle out?
最好是
i wish.
如果能量再继续堆积
if the power continues to build like this,
星门将会超过负荷
the gate will reach critical overload
最后很有可能会爆炸
and most certainly explode.
爆炸?
explode?!
我说过了这对我们非常非常不利
yes, i told you it was very, very bad for us.
怎么会这样
how does something like this happen?
我不知道  以前没发生过
i don't know. it's never happened before.
我们还有多长时间?
how long do we have?
一点不长  大概90秒
not long at all. about 90 seconds.
90秒!
90 seconds?!
应该是快到60秒了
i would say closer to 60.
马上疏散楼里的人员
we've got to evacuate everyone in the tower.
星门爆炸等效于
the gate exploding is equivalent to
数个原子弹的威力
a dozen nuclear explosions.
我们没有地方
there's nowhere we could evacuate
可以撤退
quickly enough to a safe distance.
那个...  用那个保护罩
the-- the shield.
什么?
what?
在星门周围布上保护罩
collapse the city's shield around the gate,
来控制爆炸
contain the explosion.
对  对  这应该有用
yes, yes, that might just work.
舱门将要在5秒后达到爆炸极限
the gate will reach a critical limit in five...
4秒...
four...
3秒...
three...
2秒...
two...
1秒
one.
不要直视冲击波!
don't look at the blast!
以前强调过!
might have mentioned that before!
我看看能不能再转移一些能量到保护罩上
i'll see if i can divert more power to the shield,
看看能不能多屏蔽掉一点辐射
see if i can block more of the radiation
现在怎么样了
and now what?
保护罩仍然在减缓冲击波带来的能量
the shield continues to diffuse the energy of the blast.
保护罩多支撑一秒种
every second it's contained within the shield,
爆炸就会越减弱一些
the explosion gets weaker.
还需要多久
how long does it take?
哦  不
oh, no.
又怎么了
what?
保护罩至少还要1分钟
the shield needs at least another minute
来吸收所有的能量
to contain the full brunt of the blast,
但是温度已经过高了
but we're frying out the emitters.
我不知道我能坚持多久
i don't know how much longer i can hold this.
关闭整个城市  转移所有能源
shut down the city, transfer all the power.
我正在试
yes, i'm trying.
所有人撤离
everyone that doesn't need to be here,
到城市另一边
get to the edge of the city.
快!  所有人!
move! everybody!
你也撤
you're going to want to get out of here.
约翰  我...
john, i--
泰勒  拜托了
teyla, please.
加油  你能做到!  瑞迪克
come on, you can do it, radek.
减弱了
it's going down.
我们肯定行
we're going to make it.
不...
no...
还不够
it's not enough.